Welcome to the fifth iteration
of our CS25 Transformers class.
So Div and I started this
class a long time ago
after seeing how transformers
and machine learning
in general and AI became
such a prevalent thing
and how we predicted
how it would become
an even bigger part of our
lives going forward, which does
seem to be the case.
So as large language models
and AI in general takes over
the world, whether it's through
things like ChatGPT or image
generation models like Sora,
video generation models like
Sora and so forth, we felt that
having a class where people are
able to come and learn about
transformers, how they work,
and especially hear from leading
experts in industry and academia
working on state-of-the-art
research in this area,
how that would be
very beneficial
to everybody's learning and help
us progress further within AI
and technology in general.
So yeah, so welcome
to our class.
So how our class works is
typically each week we invite
a leading researcher from either
industry or academia to come
speak about some
state-of-the-art topic
they're working on
in transformers.
So we have an exciting
lineup of speakers prepared
for you guys this quarter.
And so this first lecture
will be delivered by us
where we'll go through the
basics of transformers.
And then we divided this
lecture a bit differently
from the previous
lectures in that we
have a section on pre-training
and data strategies,
and then a section focused
more on post-training,
which has become a very
popular topic these days.
We'll also touch briefly on some
applications of transformers
and some remaining
weaknesses or challenges
that we should hopefully address
to be able to further improve
the state of AI and our
machine learning models.
So yeah.
I forgot I have control.
Yeah, so we'll start with
some instructor introductions.
So we have a good team
of co-instructors.
So my name is Steven.
I'm a current third
year CS PhD here.
Previously did my undergrad
at Waterloo in Canada.
I've done some research
in industry as well
at Amazon and NVIDIA.
And in general, my research
hovers around natural language
processing, so machine
learning for language and text
looking at things
like, can we improve
the controllability
and reasoning models
of large language models?
And more recently, cognitive
science and psychology
inspired work especially
bridging the gap, the data
gap and the learning
efficiencies between machine
learning models and
how the humans learn,
how human children learn,
and how our brains are
able to learn so efficiently.
Also done some work with
multimodal as well as computer
vision, so things like diffusion
models and image generation.
And just for fun, I also run
the piano club here with Karan.
And we have an upcoming
concert on April 11
in case you guys are interested.
Hi everyone.
I'm Karan, a second year
electrical engineering PhD
student.
I did my undergrad
at Cal Poly San Luis
Obispo after which I was
a research scientist here
now doing my PhD.
I'm a little bit more on the
medical imaging and computer
vision side.
So a lot of my current
work is at the intersection
of computer vision
and neuroscience
working with things like
fMRI and ultrasound.
And I currently work at
the STAI lab, a new lab
under Dr. Ehsan Adeli.
Hi, everyone, I'm Chelsea.
I'm a first year master's
student in symbolic systems.
And my general
research interests
are in multi-agentic frameworks,
self-improving AI agents,
and overall, just kind of
improving the interpretability
and explainability of models.
So previously, I studied
applied math and neuroscience,
and I did a bunch of
interdisciplinary research
in computer vision,
robotics, cognitive science,
things of that.
And currently, I'm working
part time at AVC firm.
And over the summer,
I'll be interning
at a conversational AI startup
as a machine learning engineer.
So I'm very interested in
exploring the startup scene here
at Stanford, so feel
free to reach out.
Hi, everyone.
I'm Jenny.
I'm a current student
majoring in synthesis as well
as a sociology co-term
here at Stanford.
My background is primarily in
technology, ethics, and policy.
So if you have any questions
or want to talk about that,
I'd love to have a conversation.
In the past, I've worked
doing product at D.E. Shaw
and also research in the
tech ethics and policy space.
And this summer, I'll
be working at Daydream,
which is an AI fashion
tech startup in New York.
And yeah, so Div was
unable to join us today,
but he's working
on his new agent
startup called AGI Inc.
Currently on leave from a CS PhD
here.
He's passionate about robotics,
AI agents, and so forth.
And later this
quarter, he'll likely
be giving a lecture actually on
everything to do with AI agents.
So if you're interested in that,
definitely look forward to it.
And previously, he's worked at
NVIDIA, Google, and so forth.
And he's the one who started
this class in the first place.
All right.
So I'll go over some of
the course logistics.
So first announcement is
we have a new website up
that's just cs25.stanford.edu.
And so all of our updates
and as well as the speaker
lineup will be posted
there in the coming weeks.
That will also be the link
to share our Zoom with people
who are not Stanford affiliated
or are on the waitlist
or have not been able to gain
admission into the class.
So we encourage everyone
to share this class
with their network and ensure
that anyone can access it
from Zoom.
Yeah, so some takeaways
from the course
include a better
understanding of transformers
and the underlying architecture
of many of our large language
models.
Guest speakers,
which will be talking
about applications in language,
vision, biology, robotics,
and more.
Exposure to new
research especially
from leading researchers
all across the country.
Innovative methods that are
driving the next generation
of models as well as key
limitations, open problems,
and the future of AI.
Sorry, I believe this is Steven
OK.
Next, I'll give a really
brief intro about transformers
and how attention works.
So the first step for
language is word embeddings.
So words aren't numbers,
so we obviously can't just
pass them into a model as is.
So the first step
is converting them
into dense vectors in a
high-dimensional space.
This is done through
various methods,
but the goal is to capture
semantic similarity.
Essentially, that
cat and dog are
more similar than
cat and car even
though the latter is more
similar from a character
standpoint.
Doing so enables
visualization, learning
with transformer models.
Or arithmetic like
I've shown like king
minus man plus queen
would approximately be
queen in some embedding space.
And classical methods for this
are like Word2Vec, FastTex,
and many more these days.
But static embeddings, for
instance, giving the word bank.
The same meaning and
just bank as in riverbank
have limitations.
Therefore, the current standard
is using contextual embeddings,
which take into account the
context and the sentence
that a word is in.
Self-attention can
be applied to this
to learn what to focus
on for a given token.
So to do this, you learn
three matrices, a query, key,
and value, which together
comprise the attention process.
A quick analogy
for this is imagine
you're in a library looking
for a book on a certain topic.
This would be your query.
Now, let's say each book
has some summary associated
with it, a key.
You can match your query and
key and get access to the book
that you're looking for.
The information inside the
book would be your value.
So in attention, we do a
soft match over the values
to get info from,
say, multiple books,
and this comprises the
attention operation.
And as you can see in
this visualization, when
you apply this to
language, you can
see that across different
layers of the model,
different words have
connections to the rest
of the words in the sentence.
The next component is positional
encodings or embeddings, which
add order to the sequence.
Without these, the
model, since you
have just linear
multiplications here,
would not know what the first
or the last word in the sentence
is.
Therefore, you add
some notion of order
through, say, sinusoids.
Or in the simplest
form, you could
think that the first word
would be zero, the second one,
the one, and on.
Beyond this is basically just
scaling through multiple layers
and multi-head
attention, more heads
to attend to different
parts of the sentence.
And more parameters
means that you
can capture more
diverse relationships
from your sequences.
And this gives you
the final transformer.
Transformers today
have overtaken
pretty much every field from
LLMs like GPT-4o, o3, DeepSeek,
to vision with models that are
getting increasingly better
at segmentation and whatnot.
Speech, biology, video, you'll
see a lot of these applications
throughout the quarter.
With large language models,
these are essentially
just scaled up versions of
attention and the transformer
architecture.
You essentially just throw
a large amount of data,
general text data derived
from the web, at these models
and they can learn
very well to model
through a next token
prediction objective language.
And as you scale up, we've seen
that emergent abilities pop up.
So while at a smaller
scale, you might not
be able to do a certain task.
Once you get to a
certain scale, you just
have a peak in the
ability to do that task.
Some disadvantages,
though, that these models
have very high computational
costs and therefore also
concerns with climate
and the carbon emissions
they may produce.
And like I was mentioning
with larger models,
they're very good at
generalizing to many abilities
or tasks, and
they're essentially
plug-and-play with few
or zero-shot learning.
All right.
So now I'll talk a bit
more about pretraining.
So as Karan explained how
the transformer works.
But typically with a
language model, especially
a large language
model, you typically
divide it into two stages,
pretraining stage where
you train the neural
network from scratch
from randomized or
initialized weights, randomly
initialized weights to give
it more general capabilities.
And a big portion of
this is the data itself.
So the data is the
fundamental fuel
that allows your model to
learn, because that's what
the model is learning from.
So your goal typically, again,
like I said with pretraining,
is to train on a
large amount of data
to obtain some sort of
general level of capabilities
and overall knowledge
or intelligence.
And this is arguably, again,
the most important aspect
of training,
especially pretraining.
Especially because
LLMs learn, again,
based on statistical
distributions predicting
the next token given
previous tokens.
So to effectively learn
this, you typically
need a large amount of data.
So because of its importance,
how do we maximally leverage it?
So again, smart data
strategies for pretraining
is definitely one of the most
important topics these days.
So I'll briefly touch
upon two of the topic
projects I recently worked
on two different scales.
The first is looking
at what makes small,
child-like data sets potentially
effective for language
learning especially
on the smaller scale.
And the second is looking
at smart data strategies
for training large models on
billions or trillions of tokens,
which is on a much larger scale.
So why are humans able
to learn so efficiently?
This looks at how human
children learn and interact
with the environment
and learn language
compared to a model
like ChatGPT, which
is a bit analogous to how
the human brain learns
language and learns in
general compared to something
like a neural network.
So some potential
key differences
are that humans
learn continuously.
We're continually learning.
We don't just pretrain.
We don't just sit
in a chair, have
someone read the
whole internet to us,
and then we just stop
learning from there.
So that's unlike a lot of
current models, which are more
single pass pretraining models.
Further, we have more
goal-based approaches
to learning and interaction
with the environment.
That's a major reason we learn.
Whereas, again, these models
are typically just pretraining
on large amounts of data
using next token prediction
or autoregression.
Further, we learned through
continuous multimodal
or multisensory data.
So it's not just text only.
We're subconsciously
exposed to probably hundreds
of sensors that guide the
way we learn and approach
our daily lives.
Further, I believe our
brains are fundamentally
different in that
we learn probably
in more structured or
hierarchical manners,
for example, through
compositionality rather
than, again, simply
next token prediction.
And the focus of this
project in particular
is more on the data differences.
So again, humans are exposed to
dialogue from people we talk to,
storybooks,
especially children--
compared to large amounts
of data on the internet.
So this is a work that
was published-- so why?
Why do you care about
small models and training
on small amounts of data?
Well, this will greatly
improve the efficiency
of training and using
large language models,
and this will open the door
to potential new use cases,
for example, models that
can run on your phone
that you can run
locally and so forth
for many different use cases.
Smaller models and
train on less data
are also more interpretable
and easier to control or align
whether it's for safety
purposes to reduce bias
and so forth to ensure people
are using them for safe reasons
and you have appropriate
guardrails in place.
This will also enhance the open
source availability allowing
research and the usage
of these models for more
people around the world
rather than simply companies
with large amounts of compute.
And in general, this might
even allow us to more
greatly understand the
other direction, which
is how humans are able to learn
so effectively and efficiently.
Yep, so this work is titled
Is Child-Directed Speech.
Effective Training Data
for Language Models,
which I presented at EMNLP
in Miami last November.
So again, the hypothesis
here is that children,
we probably learned
fundamentally different
from LLMs.
This is why we're able to
learn on several magnitudes
less language data, in
particular than many
of these large language
models these days, which
require trillions of tokens.
Now, there's several hypotheses.
One is the data we receive
as humans is different
fundamentally from LLMs.
Rather than just training
on internet data,
we actually interact
with people.
We talk to people.
We hear stories that our
parents or teachers tell us
and so forth.
The other is maybe
the human brain just
fundamentally learns different.
So our learning
algorithm is just
different from large
language models.
And another is maybe it's the
way or the structure in which we
receive this data.
So any data we receive is
somewhat curricularized.
We start off with simple data,
simple language as a child
and then learn more
complex grammars.
We hear more complex
speech from our parents,
co-workers, and so forth.
Anything we do whether
it's learning math,
we start simple and then move
on to more difficult problems.
Whereas language
models, you typically
don't care too much about
ordering or curriculum,
so there's multiple
different hypotheses here.
So in order to test some
of these, what we did
is we trained some small
GPT-2 and RoBERTa models
on five different data sets.
One is CHILDES which is
a natural conversation
data with children.
So this is transcribed.
And then we collected
a synthetic version
called TinyDialogues, which
I'll discuss more later.
BabyLM, which is
a diverse mixture
of different types of data.
This includes Reddit data,
Wikipedia data, and so forth.
So this is closer to your
typical large language model
pretraining data.
And then we also
did a bit of testing
with Wikipedia as
well OpenSubtitles,
so movie and TV transcriptions.
So we collected
TinyDialogues, and this
was inspired by the fact
that a lot of, again, I said,
our learning as children
is through conversations
with other people.
And conversations
naturally lead to learning.
We talk to someone.
They give us feedback.
We reflect on how the
conversation went.
So it's both pure
and self-reflection.
Furthermore, conversations
lead to not only learning
of knowledge but other things
like ethics and morals,
for example, parents or
teachers telling us as children
what's right or wrong to do.
And there's many different
types of conversations
you can have with many
different types of people
leading to a lot of
diversity and learning.
So what we did is
we collected a fully
grammatical and
curricularized conversation
data set with a limited
child-like restricted
vocabulary using GPT-4, and we
collected different examples
that differ by child age,
the different participants
in the conversation,
and so forth.
And here's just some
examples of some data points
in our collected data set.
So you see, as the age goes up,
the utterances or conversations
become more complex.
They become longer.
The participants also
differ by age appropriately.
So we also ran an experiment,
a curriculum experiment
where we ordered either
by ascending age order.
So the model will first see
two-year-old conversations
and then five-year-old
conversations and then
10-year-old, and so forth,
versus descending order.
Maybe it's possible a
language model might actually
learn somehow better from
more complex examples first
and then of course the typical
baseline of randomly shuffling
all your data examples.
So we have some basic
evaluation metrics targeted
at fundamental capabilities.
One is basic grammatical
and syntactic knowledge,
and another is a
free word association
metric called Word
Similarity for assessing
more semantic knowledge.
So you see here from
the different data sets
that actually it seems like
training on child-like data
is worse than a
heterogeneous mixture of just
internet data like BabyLM.
So both metrics degrade quite
substantially especially
on CHILDES, the more
natural conversation
data set between children
and their caregivers.
And you'll see, in
terms of curriculum,
we don't see many substantial
differences no matter
what order you provide the
examples into the model, which
is, again, surprising,
because, as humans, we go
from simple to more difficult.
So looking more closely at
convergence behavior or loss
curves, you'll see
here that the training
loss, has these sorts of--
a cyclical, depending on the
buckets you use for curriculum.
But the validation loss,
which is what you really
care about so the
generalization and learning, it
has the exact same
trend no matter
what order you feed the
examples in, which is, again,
a very interesting finding.
So overall, we see that diverse
data sources like BabyLM
seem to provide
a better learning
signal for language models than
purely child-directed speech.
And we do see, however,
that our TinyDialogues data
set noticeably outperforms the
natural conversation data set,
likely because that data set
is very noisy whereas ours
is, again, synthetically
collected by GPT-4.
And again, global
developmental ordering
using curriculum learning
seems to have negligible impact
on performance.
So overall, we can
conclude that it's possible
that other aspects of
children's learning,
not simply the data
they're exposed to,
are responsible for their
efficient language learning,
for example, learning from
other types of information
like multimodal information, or
it's the fact that our learning
algorithm in our brain is
just fundamentally different
and more data efficient than
language modeling techniques.
So if you wish to learn more, we
have our data set released on.
Hugging Face as
well as on GitHub.
And the papers up
on arXiv as well.
So now, let's go bigger scale.
So we were investigating
small models
trained on small amounts of
data similar to a human child.
Now what about current large
models, billions of parameters
trained on trillions of tokens?
So during my last
summer internship,
I worked on a project with
NVIDIA titled Maximize Your
Data's Potential,
Enhancing LLM Accuracy
with Two-Phase Pretraining.
So this is the optimized
data selection as well as
training strategies in
large scale pre-training.
So a lot of works like Llama
highlighted the effectiveness
of different sorts
of data mixtures,
but they don't really shed
light into the exact mixtures
and how these
decisions were made.
Whereas, we know data
blending and ordering
is crucial to effective
LLM pretraining.
So can we shed
more light on this,
which is what our work does?
So firstly, we formalize
and systematically
evaluate this concept of
two-phase pre-training.
And we show that,
empirically, it
improves over continuous
training, which is typically
what's done with LLM
training, and you just
feed in all the data
rather than separating it
into particular buckets
or a different schedule.
We also do a
fine-grained analysis
of data blending for these
two pretraining phases.
And we have this notion of
prototyping blends on smaller
token counts before scaling up.
So this two-phase
pretraining approach
is inspired kind of by how
pretraining and post-training
works, which is the first
phase is on more general data.
So this is to
learn more broadly.
So it's on more diverse data.
And the second is
to shift to more
high-quality, domain-specific
data such as math and so forth.
However, it's important
to balance between quality
and diversity in both
phases, as if you
operate any data set too much,
it can lead to overfitting.
So firstly, does two-phase
training actually help?
So we found that all
our Phase 2 blends
or our two-phase
pretraining experiments
outperformed the baseline of
simply just continuing training
on a single phase.
And this is noticeably better
than just a randomized mixture
of both phases, as well
as the natural data
distribution compared
to our upsampled data
distribution for Phase 2.
And we also showed that this
is able to scale both on model
scale and data scale.
So if you pull up the token
counts as well as the model
size, we show that
performance further
improves with our two-phase
pretraining compared
to a single phase.
So this highlights
also the effectiveness
of prototyping on smaller
data blends before scaling up.
And furthermore, we
investigated the phase,
the duration of Phase 2.
So should we train on
diverse data for a little bit
and immediately switch to highly
specialized data like math,
or should we wait longer?
And what we found is
performance improves up
to a point around 40% until
there's diminishing returns
likely from overfitting.
Because specialized data,
it's more specialized.
There's typically a
lower number of it,
and it's less diverse compared
to things like web crawl data.
So too much of it can lead
to detrimental or diminishing
returns.
So overall, we see a
well-structured two-phase
pretraining approach, with
careful data selection
and management, is essential
for optimizing LLM performance
while maintaining
scalability and robustness
across different
downstream tasks.
And in case you're
interested, this paper
is also-- preprint
is up on arXiv.
So I guess the overall takeaway
from these two projects
and what I wanted to
get at is on the fact
that data effectiveness
especially for pretraining,
it's not just the
amount of data,
but it's about the
quality of the data,
the ordering and
structure of data,
and how exactly you use it.
So for our first
project, we saw there's
negligible impact of global
order in small-scale training.
But we saw that phase-based
training for larger scales
is highly effective.
And in general,
smart data decisions
are essential for models
to generalize across tasks.
So takeaway is our
research underscores
that effective language modeling
isn't just about amassing data
but about smarter
data organization that
harnesses its structure,
quality, and characteristics.
And by continuing to refine
data-centric approaches,
the future of LLM
training promises
smarter, more efficient,
and highly adaptable models.
So now, we'll be moving
to the second stage
after pretraining
which is post-training,
which Chelsea will talk about.
All right.
So we have a pre-trained
model, now what?
How do we adapt to specific
tasks and different domains?
So some major strategies include
fine-tuning, for instance,
like reinforcement learning
with human feedback
or some prompt-based methods,
or some of RAG architecture
and retrieval-based methods.
So one major approach is called
chain-of-though reasoning.
I'm sure you all have
heard of it by now.
So it's essentially a prompting
technique to think step by step.
So it shows the intermediate
steps, provide guidance,
and this is similar to
the way how humans think.
We can imagine that we
typically break down a problem
into subsequent steps
to help us better
understand the problem itself.
And another benefit
of chain of thought
is that it allows some
of interpretable window
into the behavior of the model.
And this can suggest that there
is more knowledge embedded
in the model's weights than
just prompting a response.
So this here is an example
of chain of thought.
On the left, we have
it solve a problem
in a one-shot manner,
which turns out
to get to the wrong answer.
And on the right over
there, it produces
a sequence of reasoning chains.
And ultimately, it arrives
at the correct answer.
So naturally, this
brings up an extension
of chain-of-thought, which
is called a tree-of-thought.
And this is another
prompting technique.
But instead of producing
a singular reasoning path
as a chain-of-thought does, it
considers multiple reasoning
trajectories and then uses some
sort of self-evaluation process
to decide on the final outputs
such as majority voting.
So in the picture, you can
see that tree-of-thought
generates different
reasoning paths
and selects the
best one at the end.
So another way is through
program-of-thought.
And this basically
generates code
as the intermediate
reasoning steps.
And overall, what
this does is that it
offloads some
problem-solving technique
to some code interpreter.
So it formalizes
language into programs
to arrive at more
precise answers.
So we have seen that this
problem decomposition seems
helpful for different tasks.
So one way is through
Socratic questioning,
which is basically using
a self-questioning module
to propose subproblems
related to the original
and solves those in
a recursive manner.
So for instance, if
the question is like,
what fills the balloons?
This leads to the next
subquestion, which is like,
what can make a balloon float?
And then by decomposing
the original problem
into subsequent problems, it
can better solve at the end.
So finally, another problem
decomposition method
is through computational graphs.
So this basically formulates
compositional tasks
as a computation
graphs by breaking down
the reasoning into different
sub-procedures and nodes.
So the key takeaway here
is that transformers
can solve compositional
tasks by reducing reasoning
into subgraphs, and this
is without developing
some systematic
problem-solving skill.
Right.
So Chelsea touched on
chain-of-thought and everything
that expands upon
it or improves it.
And that's mainly a
prompting-based method
for inference time.
Next, I'll be talking
more at reinforcement
learning and feedback
mechanisms, which are typically
used for things like further
fine-tuning a pre-trained model.
So the most popular
is this thing
called Reinforcement Learning
with Human Feedback or RLHF.
So this trains a reward model
directly from human feedback.
So you do is you take
your pre-trained model,
get it to generate
several responses,
and then you typically take
a pair, a pair of responses
and have humans rate
which one they prefer.
And you can train a reward
model based on this basically
using a reinforcement
learning optimization
algorithm such as PPO.
Now, there's an improvement
to PPO called DPO or Direct
Preference Optimization.
So this more directly
trains the model
to prefer outputs that
humans rank higher
compared to having a
separate reward model, which
is much more efficient.
So basically, you
can think of it
as it more closely ties the
reward directly into the loss
function itself by helping
the LLM to maximize
the likelihood of generating
preferred responses
and minimize the
likelihood of the responses
that humans did not prefer.
And there's a extension to
RLHF, which is called RLAIF.
So this is simply replacing
the human with an AI.
So you typically have
a pretty good LLM
that's able to provide accurate
preference judgments of which
response it prefers.
And this is less
costly basically
compared to human annotators.
And then basically
you do the same thing.
You train a reward model
based on the LLM's preferences
instead.
And actually, human evaluators
found that RLAIF-tuned outputs
were similar to RLHF,
showing that this
is a more scalable and
cost-efficient approach compared
to human feedback.
But there's one
disadvantage here,
which is it really depends on
the capabilities or the accuracy
of judgments of the
LLM you're using
to provide your preferences.
So if you're using one that
is incapable or very noisy,
then that's going to
hurt your post-training.
The next is this
thing very hot now
which was used in
DeepSeek both their R1,
as well as some other
models, like their math ones.
So this is called Group Relative
Policy Optimization or GRPO.
So this is a variant of the
PPO optimization algorithm.
But rather than ranking
simply pairs of responses,
it actually ranks a group of
responses in a different order.
So this provides
richer feedback,
which is more
fine-grained and is
much more efficient compared to
simply ranking pairs of outputs.
So this helps
stabilize training,
which is one reason DeepSeek
is very much more data
and compute efficient.
And also, they saw
that it improves
even things like LLM reasoning
especially on things like math.
There's also been other
variations of RLHF and so forth.
One is this thing called
Kahneman-Tversky Optimization.
Not sure if I'm pronouncing
that correctly, but KTO.
So this modifies the standard
loss function typically used
in post-training
things to account
for human biases such
as loss aversion.
So as humans, we care
more about minimizing
disastrous or negative outcomes
than achieving positive ones.
We're more risk averse
in the most case,
although it's very
dependent on the person.
So they encouraged the AI to
behave in a similar manner
by avoiding negative
outcomes, and this basically
adjusts the training
process to reflect this.
And they showed that this is
able to improve performance
on different tasks, although
it depends on the task.
But overall, it shows
more human-like behavior
on particular tasks.
And these are just a subset
of the RLHF and reinforcement
learning and
feedback-based algorithms.
One I want to touch
upon before I finish off
is this thing
called personalizing
RLHF with the variational
preference learning.
So the authors saw that
different demographics
have different preferences.
So typical RLHF averages
everything together.
So what the authors do is
they introduce a latent
variable for every user
preference profile,
for example, a
different demographic
like children,
adults, and so forth
and trains reward models
conditioned on these latent
vectors or factors.
So this leads to something they
call pluralistic alignment,
which is improving
the reward accuracy
for these particular
demographics or subgroups.
So it enables a single
model to adapt its behavior
to different preference profiles
and different demographics
or groups of people.
And now, I'll hand
it back to Chelsea
to talk about self-improving.
All right.
So yeah, let's talk a little bit
about self-improving AI agents.
So what exactly is an AI agent?
So it's essentially a system
that perceives the environment,
makes decisions and takes
actions towards achieving
some specific goal.
And usually, this goal is given
by the human so for instance
like game-playing, task-solving,
or research assistance.
And there are several
components of an AI agent.
So, one, it's goal-directed.
Two, it can make
its own decisions.
Three, it can act iteratively.
Four, there's usually some
memory component to it
and state tracking
component to it.
And finally, there's
some agents that
can use some tools such as
API calls or function calling.
And finally, it can learn
and adapt on its own.
OK.
Yeah.
So self-improvement,
basically, models
can reflect on their own
outputs leading to iterative
improvements over time.
So this typically
consists of several steps.
There's some reflection of
its own internal states.
There's an explanation of
its own reasoning process.
It can evaluate the
quality of its own outputs.
And finally, it can also
simulate multi-step reasoning
chains.
So one technique is refinement.
So this is where you have some
iterative prompting technique
where an LLM critiques and
improves its own outputs.
So it generates some
initial response
and then refines it over time.
And this uses feedback loops to
enhance the overall performance.
So an example would be
it generates some answer
and then it evaluates itself for
weaknesses and inconsistencies.
And finally, it
refines the response
based on the own
self-critique method.
Another technique is
called self-reflection.
So this is where a model
learns from past mistakes
and adjusts future responses
based on past failures.
So there usually is some
long-term memory component
to this.
And an example would be
like the model first detects
some of weak response
from its own outputs,
and then it reflects
on its own mistakes
and generates some
improved answer to it.
And over multiple iterations,
accuracy and reasoning
should improve over time.
Another technique is called
ReAct, which is essentially
just combining reasoning with
external actions such as API
calls or retrievals
from a database.
And this is basically some model
that can interact dynamically
with its environment.
So it gets feedback from taking
multiple action sequences
and incorporating
that into its outputs.
So for instance, the model
will generate a reasoning plan,
and then it will call some
external tool such as web search
or some API call,
and then this model
incorporates the retrieved
data into its final response.
And finally, this leads us to a
framework called Language Agent
Tree Search.
So basically what
LATS is is that it
extends the ReAct framework to
incorporate multiple planning
pathways.
So you can think this like
analogous to chain-of-thought
versus tree-of-thought.
It gathers feedback
from every path
to improve the future
search process, which
is some verbal reinforcement
learning-inspired technique.
And it uses Monte
Carlo Tree Search
to optimize planning
trajectories,
where in the tree structure,
every node represents a state
and every edge represents an
action that the agent can take.
So an example would be it
generates N best new action
sequences, and then it will just
execute them all in parallel.
Then it will use some
self-reflection technique
to score each one,
and then overall,
just continue exploring
from the best state
and update the probabilities
of the past node.
And yeah.
All right.
Next, I'll be talking about
a few other applications
of transformers
outside of language.
I'll start with Vision
Transformers which
have taken vision by storm.
The methodology here is that--
so as I talked about
transformers taking sequences,
but images aren't sequences.
However, what the authors of
the ViT paper came up with
was to split an image up
into patches, which can then
be embedded to form a sequence.
Passing this through
a simple transformer
yielded very good results, for
instance, on classification,
just by adding an
MLP head to the end.
You might ask why apply
transformers to this problem
when CNNs are such a
mainstay in the field.
The main reason is that when
you have a very large data set,
say, in the tens of
millions of examples,
transformers bring in
less inductive biases.
CNNs assume locality and that
pixels are grouped together.
Whereas with transformers
and treating your images
as sequences, you can
see better results
when you have enough
data to train them.
One common architecture
that was impacted by this
was CLIP, which uses ViTs
for its image encoders.
This is the basis of
models like GPT-4o
or other vision-language
models and essentially works
through contrastive learning.
So you take a data set of
paired images and text pairs,
and you train your model
to align the encoder
representations of both.
So if you have an image of
a cat and and the word cat,
then you can learn to
align those embeddings.
And like I mentioned, these have
been applied to vision-language
models like GPT-4 or 4o.
The way these are trained is you
concatenate your encoded image
and text, and you can
train in different stages
such that your model
learns to take both
and to account
for its responses.
And these have done very
well on benchmarks and tasks
for instance like test
questions like I've shown here.
Next, I'll talk about a bit
of my work and neuroscience,
which applies ViTs to
other kinds of data.
So a mainstay in my field is
functional magnetic resonance
imaging, or fMRI.
Essentially, this captures
the amount of oxygen
that each voxel part of your
brain is using at a given point,
and this provides a very
detailed proxy for the activity
going on in your brain.
It can be used to diagnose
diseases and capture
various amounts of data for
better cognitive understanding.
However, this is very
high dimensional.
You might have a million or so
voxels or 100,000 in the brain.
So the first step to using this
data with transformer models
is usually averaging
across well-known regions
or just grouping
together voxels,
and this gives you a more
computationally tractable number
of parcels that
you can train on.
A traditional tool in this field
was just to use linear pairwise
correlation maps, and just these
were enough to get pretty good
diagnoses of things
like Parkinson's.
However, with the advent of tons
of computer vision techniques,
we can apply larger
and more sophisticated
models to these tasks.
One cool, large body
of work in this area
is divvying up the brain into
different functional networks,
so let's say like your vision
system or your daydreaming
network or control, et cetera.
And I'll get into how we
use this to guide our work.
So like I mentioned,
early ML models
just took like linear
correlation maps
so making lots of
assumptions about the data
and just applied typical
neural networks to the task
for regression or classification
tasks or, in some cases,
graph-based analyses
to try to get a deeper
understanding of how the
different parts of the brain
interact with each other.
With computer vision,
we can take our raw data
and just throw that at
a transformer model,
and that does very well as
a pre-training objective.
So what we do is let's say
we have some number of ROIs
across time, we can just mask
out some portion of that data,
pass the rest of the data
through a transformer model,
and have it predict
this portion.
You repeat this across a large
data set and all of your ROIs,
and this provides a very
good self-supervised training
objective for this task.
So self-supervised
essentially means that there
is no paired labeled data here.
We are essentially
just using our raw data
and posing our
objective such that we
can learn directly off of it.
Once you've trained
this model, you
have these dense representations
inside the model that
can be applied downstream
to various tasks
like predicting
patient attributes
or their risk of disease.
And you can also
look at the weights
that your model has learned
to analyses of brain networks.
So in brief, our
approach essentially
consists of taking the
activity in the entire brain,
partitioning out
some small region,
let's say it's
your vision system.
You pass the unmasked portion
into a transformer model, which
learns to predict
the masked portion,
and you can compare this
to your ground truth
to provide your
training objective.
One key thing we use
here is cross-attention.
So what we talked about
before with language
was self-attention,
wherein you are
attending to the current
sequence you're looking at.
In cross-attention, you have
two different sequences.
Let's say in machine
translation you have one
in English and in French.
And essentially,
you apply attention
between the two
sequences instead
of just on a single sequence.
So our most basic architecture
takes advantage of this
through just a singular
cross-attention decoder.
Having a very small model makes
for better interpretability.
And like I mentioned,
this model just
learns to predict masked brain
regions from unmasked ones.
Once we've done this, we can
analyze again the attention
weights to gain a deeper
understanding of networks
and also apply this
to downstream tasks.
So some modeling results.
Here, I've plotted
like the brain activity
from different patients.
And you can see that the
model does pretty well
in matching the ground
truth for two networks
that I've shown here, the
salience network, which
is involved in your senses
and decision making,
and the Default Mode
Network or DMN, which
is responsible for daydreaming
or just recapitulating
your brain information when
you're not doing a certain task.
On the bottom, we have
the attention weights
for this model, which I've split
up by all of the other networks.
So for instance,
on the left, when
predicting the salience network,
we can see from our model
that it is heavily dependent
on the default mode and control
networks.
So this gives us a
better understanding
of how different brain networks
are connected to each other
or how they might share
information inside the brain.
For other networks, though, like
vision, these are more singular.
We can't predict them very well.
Or subcortical regions, say,
those involved in memory,
we also cannot
predict very well.
So this is all well and cool.
We can predict brain
activity, but what can
we do with this model?
If we simply replace
one component
of the model with a learnable
token, which corresponds
to predicting
Parkinson's disease,
then we can use this model
to predict that ailment.
So if you look on the right,
after some fine tuning
on a labeled data set, we
can see some clustering
in the model's embedding,
which corresponds
to getting close to 70%
accuracy in predicting
this disease, which is
much higher than using
the correlation-based based
methods or linear assumptions
that I talked about earlier.
All right.
So now that we have some
background on these transformer
models and a couple
of their applications,
let's talk about the
future and what's next.
So overall, these
transformer models
can enable a lot
more applications
across every
industry and sector.
This includes generalist
agents as well as longer video
understanding and generation
across the finance and business
sector, domain-specific
foundation models like,
for example, one could imagine
a DoctorGPT or a LawyerGPT
or an "insert field" GPT as well
as potential real-world impacts
like personalized education
and tutoring systems,
advanced healthcare diagnostics,
environmental monitoring
and protection, real-time
multilingual communication
as well as in interactive
environment and gaming,
for example,
non-playable characters.
What is missing though?
What information might
we need and what can we
develop in the future?
Currently, we're missing
reducing computation complexity,
enhancing human controllability,
alignment with the language
models of the human
brain, adaptive learning
and generalization across
different domains, and finally,
multi-sensory, multimodal
embodiment like intuitive
physics and commonsense.
So one might consider
these barriers
to developing artificial
general intelligence,
and these are some
of the limitations
of current transformer models.
Some other things
that are missing
include infinite
and external memory,
like Neural Turing Machines,
infinite self-improvement
capabilities like continual
or lifelong learning.
This is another central
tenet of human learning
that we're not able to
replicate at the moment.
Complete autonomy, including
curiosity, desires, and goals,
and long-horizon
decision-making, as well as
emotional intelligence,
social understanding,
and of course, ethical
reasoning and value alignment.
All right.
So there's still a plethora
of remaining weaknesses
or challenges around
transformers, large language
models, and AI in
general these days,
so I'll touch upon a
couple of them briefly.
The first is, like I mentioned
earlier, efficiency, being
able to minify or have tiny
LLMs or models that you
can run on your phone, on
your smartwatch, et cetera.
So that's a big
trend these days is
using LLMs for everyday
applications and purposes.
And again, you want to be able
to run them quickly and easily
on smaller devices.
Right now, there
is more and more
work on smaller
and more efficient
open-source models, things like
DeepSeek, LLaMA and Mistral,
but they're still somewhat
large and a bit expensive
especially if you're
looking to finetune.
They're still not accessible
to everybody especially
on smaller devices.
So in the future,
again, we want to aim
to have the ability to finetune
or run these models locally
on whatever device you want.
The second is as our models,
as our LLMs scale up,
trillions of parameters
trained on trillions of tokens
across the internet,
what happens
is this makes it a
huge black-box that
is difficult to
understand or interpret.
It's hard to know what exactly
is going on behind the scenes.
When you ask it to solve
XYZ, and it comes up
with answers ABC, how
exactly did it get there?
Why did it choose
those answers instead?
And so forth.
So more work on interpretability
for LLMs will give us
a better idea of what
or how to improve them,
easier ways of controlling
them, and better
alignment, for example,
being able to prevent them
from producing
certain outputs that
might be unsafe or unethical.
So there's this area, which
has gotten even more popular
recently called mechanistic
interpretability, which
is trying to understand
how individual components
or operations, even sometimes
down to the individual node
level, so very
granular, in an ML model
contribute to its overall
decision-making process
with the goal, again, of
unpacking this black-box
for clear insight on how exactly
they work behind the scenes.
Next, I feel like
we're approaching
or we're already seeing
diminishing returns
with simply scaling up.
So larger models on
more data does not
seem to be the be-all,
end-all solution.
So one-size-fits-all and frozen
pre-trained models have already
started, leading to
diminishing returns.
So again, pre-training
performance.
So the first half of training
LLMs, it's likely saturating.
Hence, there's been more focus
on post-training methods.
Everything we've talked about,
feedback and RL mechanisms,
and prompting methods
like chain-of-thought,
self-improvement and
refinement and so forth.
However, all of these
post-training mechanisms
are going to be
fundamentally limited
by the overall performance or
capabilities of the base model.
So you can argue that the
pre-training is fundamentally
what gives the basis or
the foundational knowledge
and capabilities to the model.
So we should not just stop
investigating pre-training
just because we're
hitting scaling limits.
Furthermore, too
much post-training
can actually lead to an issue.
This is called
catastrophic forgetting
where the model forgets stuff
it's learned beforehand.
For example, during
pre-training, because you're
overloading it with
tons of new information
in a new domain or a new
task during post-training.
So how do we break through
this scaling law limit?
Some potential
things to investigate
would be new architectures.
There are different things like
Mamba, state space machines,
those architectures,
and it would
be good to see more
investigation on even
non-transformer
architectures, which
is a bit ironic considering this
class is transformers united,
but we always encourage
more diversity
and thinking outside the box.
Also again, everything I
talked about high-quality data
and smart data ordering
and structuring
strategies and overall
improved training
procedures, improved
algorithms, loss functions,
optimization algorithms
and so forth.
Another goal, as we've
mentioned several times,
is to be able to bring these
advanced capabilities to smaller
models.
Furthermore, we
would still encourage
more theoretical and
interpretability research
including things like
cognitive science
and neuroscience-inspired
work, which
Karan and I have talked
about some of that
that we've done recently.
And so the next step will be
models that are not just larger,
but ones that are more
smarter and more adaptable.
So again, there's this one
major thing or major weakness
that I think still
bridges the gap between AI
and humans, which is continual
or lifelong learning so
AI systems that can
continuously improve by learning
after deployment,
after being pre-trained
using implicit feedback,
real-word world
experience, and so forth.
So essentially, this is
infinite and permanent
fundamental self-improvement.
We're not just talking
about RAG or retrieval
like putting knowledge
in a retrieval database
that you can
retrieve at test time
but updating the brain or
the weights of the model
continuously.
So this is similar to us.
So we're learning every day.
I'm learning right
now by talking to you.
I learn every time I
talk to somebody else
as I'm going through
my daily life.
But these models, after
they're frozen or pre-trained,
that doesn't really happen.
They only way they truly learn
or their brain or weights are
updated is through finetuning.
And again, we don't do that.
We don't sit-in a chair
every three months
and have someone reread
the internet to us
or something like that.
So again, this is
almost wasted work.
So currently during
inference, the models
are not actually learning
and updating their weights.
When they're talking, when
ChatGPT is talking to you,
it's not truly updating
its brain or weights.
So this is a very challenging
problem but in our opinion
is likely one of the
keys potentially to AGI
or truly human-like AI systems.
So there's different current
work that tries to tackle this.
There's things like finetuning
a smaller model based
on traces from a larger model,
things like model distillation
related to a lot of things
like improvement and so forth.
But this is, again, not
truly continual learning.
So some questions are, what
mechanisms could potentially
truly enable real
lifelong learning
and will this be
gradient updates?
So actually updating the brain.
Will it be things like
targeting particular nodes
in the architecture?
Will it be having things like
particular memory architectures
or different parts of the
neural network solely focused
on continuous updates and
learning or even things
meta-learning learning
and looking more
at the broad scale of
things or the broader scope?
So one line of work which
has seen a bit of traction
is model editing.
So this is related to work on
mechanistic interpretability.
So instead of updating
the whole model,
if we're given a new
fact or a new data point,
can we target specific nodes
or neurons in the model
that we should update?
So one work called Rank-One
Model Editing or ROME
tries to do this through
causal intervention mechanisms
to determine which
neuron activations
most correspond to particular
factual predictions
and then updating
them appropriately.
But as you can possibly suspect,
this has a lot of weaknesses.
So firstly, this works mainly
for knowledge-based things
or simple facts.
What if we want to
update the actual skills
or capabilities of a model?
We want it to be better
at math in general.
We want it to be better at
advanced analogical reasoning,
unlike humans.
Then something
like model editing
based on factual predictions
doesn't seem like it'll work.
The second is these are
targeting one fact at a time,
so it's not easy to propagate
these changes to other nodes
based on related facts.
For example, let's
say someone's mother,
we want to update
a fact about them,
then we should
also update a fact
about that person's
brother, because they
have the same mother.
But this approach
will only update it
for the original
person in question,
but not any of the relatives.
So this is just one example.
So there's a lot of other works
which have spun out recently
in continual learning, which
is good that this area has
seen more work.
So I will very briefly
describe some of these.
One is this thing called MEMIT,
which is directly related
to what I just said about
ROME, but it's mass editing
of factual knowledge.
So instead of a simple
fact or memory at a time,
it's able to simultaneously
modify thousands, even
ones which might be related
to each other, like I said,
which is useful.
There's things, that CEM or
Continue Evolving from Mistakes.
So it actually identifies
the LLM mistakes
somewhat similar to what
self-improvement Chelsea was
talking about but
incrementally updates
the model to self-improve.
There's things like
lifelong mixture of experts.
So what it does is instead of
having a simple, fixed mixture
of experts architecture, it
continually adds new experts
for different domains over time
while freezing potentially past
experts which are
no longer useful
or don't need to be
updated to avoid things
like catastrophic forgetting.
So this is a very
smart approach.
Another is called CLOB.
So this enables continual
task learning using only
prompting without updating
model weights by summarizing
past knowledge into a
compressed prompt memory.
However, not a criticism of
this work, but again, this
is not technically
updating the brain
or the fundamental
capabilities of the model,
so this is more of a
prompt-only approach.
And another one of these is
called progressive prompts,
which, again, alerts a soft
prompt vector for each task
and, again, progressively
compresses them
and composes them together.
So allowing LLMs to
continually learn
without weight updates or
catastrophic forgetting.
But again, my opinion is
true continual learning would
update the brain or the weights
of the model in some way,
I guess.
So thanks.
That's mainly our lecture.
So we gave a brief overview of
transformers, how they work.
Talked about pre-training
and especially
how data is important for that.
Various post-training
techniques, feedback mechanisms,
prompting mechanisms
like chain-of-thought,
self-improvement, some
applications to neuroscience,
vision, and so forth, and some
remaining weaknesses like things
like the lack of continual
learning and data efficiency,
being able to scale down and
run these models on our phone.
So before we send you guys off--
I know we ended a bit early--
so this class going
forwards, every week,
in case you haven't attended,
we'll have a speaker,
typically from
industry or academia,
come in to talk about
the state-of-the-art work
they're doing.
And we have a cool
lineup of speakers
prepared for you guys for
the remainder of the quarter.
And some more logistical things.
We'll be posting
updates about lectures
and so forth on our
website through the mailing
list, Discord, and
so forth, so please
join those if you
haven't already.
Thank you, guys.
Hope you enjoyed
the first lecture.
And if anybody
has any questions,
feel free to come
up and stay around.
But thanks.
[APPLAUSE]